Finding Aid for Thomas Mitchell Sawyer papers, 1951-1998
Bentley Historical Library, University of Michigan
Thomas Mitchell Sawyer papers 1951-1988
Sawyer, Thomas Mitchell, 1917-
1 linear foot
89140 Aa 2
Professor of humanities in the College of Engineering of the University of Michigan. Reminiscences and family history; files relating to his administrative responsibilities at the University; essay written by Jan Veering, and edited by Sawyer, describing Veering's year in Ann Arbor, Michigan, as a visiting Dutch scholar to the University of Michigan.
Bentley Historical Library, University of Michigan
The collection was the gift of Professor Sawyer (donor no. 3867 ) and came to the library in 1988.
The collection is open without restriction, except for 1 folder which is closed until 2013.
Thomas M. Sawyer was born in Hillsdale, Michigan, November 11, 1917. He is the descendent of two University of Michigan regents, Walter H. Sawyer and Austin E. Wing. After receiving a bachelor's degree in biology at Kenyon College (1939), Sawyer taught English in Pearl Harbor, Hawaii, where he experienced the Japanese attack. During World War II, Sawyer served as an ambulance driver in the American Field Service from 1943 to 1945. In 1945 Sawyer came back to Michigan and began a teaching career as a professor of humanities in the College of Engineering at the University of Michigan, while he worked toward a master's degree (1947) and a PhD (1953) in the field of speech. Professor Sawyer served as chairman of the College's Department of Humanities from 1966 to 1971. He retired from active teaching in 1986 and was later named professor emeritus of humanities by the Board of Regents.
The Sawyer papers have been arranged into two series: Reminiscences and Family History which provides personal information on Sawyer and relates to memorable experiences during World War II and travels abroad and University Activities which is comprised of materials relating to Sawyer's activities at the University of Michigan in the period 1951-1986.
Subjects:
Ann Arbor (Mich.); Sawyer, Thomas Mitchell, 1917-; University of Michigan. College of Engineering.; University of Michigan--Faculty.
Contributors:
Veering, Jan.
- Biographical / Personal
  Biographical / Personal includes memoirs intended for Sawyer's grandchildren and relates in part to his experiences during World War II and observations while traveling in Pakistan (1963-64). This series includes some genealogical material and a copy of Jan Veering's "Speaking About Writing--An Academic Year in Ann Arbor" published in the Netherlands, and edited by Thomas Sawyer. Veering was a visiting Dutch scholar at the University of Michigan.
  - Reminiscences and Family History: "Personal Notes for my Children and Grandchildren" 1986 and 1998 (Box 1)
    (2 editions)
  - "Speaking About Writing--An Academic Year in Ann Arbor" by Jan Veering, edited by Thomas Sawyer, 1972 (Box 1)
- University Activities
  University Activities is comprised of correspondence, spanning nearly all of Sawyer's professional affiliation with the University of Michigan (1951-1986). The correspondence covers such topics as curriculum development, humanities issues, student recommendations and discussions of his publications. Included are Department of Humanities newsletters (1971-1981), also memoranda and correspondence from Sawyer's committee work. Both the newsletters and the committee material address problems in curriculum development as well as other issues in the Department of Humanities.
  - Correspondence, 1951-1986, 11 folders (Box 1)
  - Departmental Newsletters, 1971-1981, 2 folders (Box 1)
  - Committee Work Related to Curriculum Development, 1965-1980 (Box 1)
  - Committee Work, 1983 (Box 1)
  - Marwil Tenure Denial Case, 1976-1983 (Box 1)
    (clippings and public documents)
  - Marwil Tenure Denial Case, 1976-1983 (Box 1)
    (correspondence, reports, etc.; closed until 2013)